Guide to the Joseph W. Reed Designs and Art Work Collection
Yale University Arts Library
Joseph W. Reed designs and art work collection.
1948-2002
AOB 5
Yale University Arts Library
10
(17 boxes + 5 broadside folders)
Collection contains personal papers, writings, and works of art, including paintings, drawings, designs, books, and other materials documenting the artistic career of Joseph W. Reed.
Reed, Joseph W., 1932-
Piratical Primrose Press
Associated Materials
Additional unprocessed Joseph Reed materials held by Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Paul Horgan, 1991, and Joseph W. Reed.
Conditions Governing Access
Curatorial permission required before use.
Biographical / Historical
Joseph W. Reed is a graduate of Yale University (B.A. 1954; M.A. 1958; Ph.D. 1961). Professor Emeritus of English and American Studies at Wesleyan University, Reed is a published author and artist working in a variety of genres, including painting, drawing, book arts, and medal design. He is particularly noted for his illustrated alphabets and his Piratical Primrose press publications.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains personal papers, writings, and works of art, including paintings, drawings, designs, books, and other materials documenting the artistic career of Joseph W. Reed.
Arrangement
Preliminarily arranged in three series: I. Personal Files, 1970-2002. II. Non-Commissioned Works, 1948-1995. III. Commissioned Works, 1972-1999.
Artists' books -- United States; Reed, Joseph W., 1932-
- Personal Files, 1970-2002; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes correspondence and other personal files, such as writings and research.
  Arrangement
  Materials are organized into the following subseries: Biographical information, Photographs, Correspondence and subject files, Writings about Reed, Writings by Reed, and Scrapbooks.
  - Biographical information (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and subject files
    - Addison-Ripley (Box 1)
    - Alphabets (Box 1)
    - Art (Box 1)
    - Estimates (Box 1)
    - Exhibitions
      - Notes (Box 1)
      - Publicity (Box 1)
      - Publicity (Folder 1)
    - Film course exams (Box 1)
    - General correspondence (Box 1)
    - Horgan, Paul (Box 1)
    - Illness
      - New York Art Multiples law (Box 1)
    - Percival Galleries, Inc. (Box 1)
    - Yale Library Associates (Box 1)
  - Writings about Reed
    - "Painting by Letter," by Christopher Reed. In Horticulture, 1982 Feb., p. 61-64. (Box 1)
  - Writings by Reed
    - American Scenarios (Box 1)
      Includes the following: book jacket; proofs; press release; paste-ups for order form; printer's layout for dust jacket.
    - Getting Started: The Beginnings of the Middletown YMCA. (Box 1)
      Includes the following: pamphlet; paste-ups with various initial letters; drawings for initial letters; correspondence regarding initial letters.
    - Three American Originals (Box 1)
      Includes sketches for cover illustration.
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      Includes the following: review of poetry manuscript for Wesleyan University Press; paste-up for announcement for lecture on satirical prints from the Lewis Walpole Library.
  - Scrapbooks containing information on Reed, 1970-1979; 2 (Box 1)
- Non-Commissioned Work, 1948-1995; Series II
  This series includes various non-commissioned artworks by Reed.
  Materials are organized into the following subseries: Alphabets; Piratical Primrose [Press]; Paintings and Watercolors; Prints; Sketches, Notes, etc.; Collages; Book Objects.
  - Alphabets
    - Alphabet, 1973; first etching; proofs and sketches (Box 1)
    - "American Icons", 1982; sketch; for Kit Reed (Box 1)
    - Autobiography, undated (Box 1)
    - Bicentennial, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Brian Aldiss (Box 1)
    - Bugs, 1979; print (Box 7)
    - Christmas sequence, 1973-1979; final state (Box 7)
    - Color, 1972; sketch (Box 1)
    - Flower Alphabet for Paul, 1975; acrylic (Box 7)
    - Flowers (Folder 1)
    - Franz Kafka, circa 1984 (Box 1)
    - Franz Kafka, circa 1984 (Folder 1)
    - "History of Western Ant", 1982; proofs and sketches (Box 1)
    - "History of Western Ant", 1982; proofs and sketches (Box 7)
    - "History of Western Ant", 1982; proofs and sketches (Folder 1)
    - Hollywood, 1972; sketches (Box 1)
    - Hollywood, 1972; sketch (Box 7)
    - Monster (Box 1)
    - Philosopher's Alphabet for Paul Horgan, undated; watercolor sketch (Box 1)
    - Richard Purdy Wilbur, undated (Box 7)
    - "26 Most Important People of the Modern Age", 1982; various states (Box 7)
    - '30s (Box 1)
    - Unidentified (Box 7)
  - Piratical Primrose [Press]
    - The Annotated Clerihew, 1984; typescripts, annotated (Box 1)
    - The Book of Lobster and Forgetting, 1987; paste-ups (Box 1)
    - The Book of the Hubbies, 1982; unbound copy; paste-ups; final version: #73/75, signed (Box 1)
    - The Book of the Hubbies, 1982 (Box 9)
    - The Brave Little Scottie, 1986; paste-ups; typescript mock-up with notations; proofs of text; final version: #89/200, signed (Box 1)
    - The Deaths of the Poets, 1991; Final versions (including 2nd edition and 3 variant bindings); typescript; paste-ups; proofs; labels (Box 1)
    - The Deaths of the Poets, 1991 (Box 12)
    - Dog Truths, 1996; manuscript and 3 illustrations (Box 1)
    - A Gallery of Clerihews, 1984; Final version; paste-ups; typescript; notes; layout dummies; original drawings for illustrations (Box 1)
    - Nature's Way, 1994; proofs and illustrations (Box 2)
    - Opera News for the Dumb, 1989; typescript with notations; original drawings; paste-ups; proofs; final version: #49/100, brown paper cover (Box 2)
    - Opera News for the Dumb, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Photoplay, 1972; final version: #12/75; additional drawings not included in final (Box 2)
    - Return of Swamp Youth for Paul Horgan's 80th birthday, 1983; sketches in pencil and watercolor; paste-ups; proofs; litho plates; and illustration screens (Box 9)
    - Return of Swamp Youth, 1983 (Box 12)
    - The Singing Marine, 1992; final version: #101/250 (Box 2)
    - Sisohpromatem, 1965; final version: #20/25 (Box 2)
    - Thirty Polite Things to Say, 1988; typescript with notations, paste-ups; final version: #116/200, signed (Box 2)
    - Thirty-One Keys to Social Success, 1995; final version: unnumbered (Box 2)
    - The Yellow Pony, 1980; final version, with original drawing: #73/100, signed (Box 2)
  - Paintings and Watercolors
    - Cicada, 1965-08; watercolor/gouaches on ivory, signed; , framed; 7 inches x 8 inches (Box 10)
    - "Clouds #1, Florida", 1984; watercolor, signed; , framed; 12 11/16 inches x 13 ½ inches (Box 8)
    - "Crickets", 1965 (Box 2)
    - "Custer at Niagara Falls" for Paul Horgan, 1979; acrylic, signed; , unframed; 11 ½ inches x 13 ½ inches (Box 10)
    - "Custer at the Institution", 1975; acrylic, signed; , unframed; 8 inches x 10 inches (Box 10)
    - "Custer Ecorchee", 1977 (Box 10)
    - "Edgar Allen Poe" for Paul Horgan, 1979; watercolor, signed (Box 2)
    - "Florida Sky", 1984-06; watercolor, signed; , framed; 12 3/4 inches x 14 inches (Box 8)
    - "General George Armstrong Custer", 1979; watercolor, signed; , framed; 5 inches x 7 inches (Box 2)
    - "General George Crook U.S.A.", 1978; watercolor, signed; , framed; 5 inches x 7 inches (Box 2)
    - "General William Tecumseh Sherman" (Box 2)
    - "The Generalissimo at the Tomb of Columbus", 1976; [acrylic?], signed; , unframed; 10 7/8 inches x 6 15/16 inches (Box 10)
    - "Henry James in New York, 1860", oil, signed; , unframed;, framed; 4 inches x 4 inches; 9 inches x 9 inches (Box 11)
    - "Ida McKinley", 1979 (Box 2)
    - "Indian Man", 1987 (Box 2)
    - "Leaves", 1964 (Box 2)
    - "Little Wolf" (Box 2)
    - "Liverpool, 1802" (History of Western Ant), 1970; [oil?], signed; , unframed;, framed; 4 inches x 4 inches; 9 inches x 9 inches (Box 10)
    - "Liverpool Station Arrangement in Black and Blue" for Paul Horgan, 1978; acrylic, signed; , framed; 11 3/4 inches x 14 inches (Box 10)
    - "Night Blooming Cereus" for Paul Horgan, 1968; acrylic, signed; , unframed; 8 3/4 inches x 8 ½ inches (Box 10)
    - "Pass-a-Grille Way", 1990; acrylic and pencil, signed; , unframed; 10 inches x 15 inches (Box 10)
    - "Paul as Richelieu" for Paul Horgan, 1984; acrylic, signed; , unframed; 12 inches x 10 inches (Box 10)
    - "Poe Ecorchee", 1977 (Box 10)
    - "Rouben Mamoulian", undated; [acrylic?], unsigned; , round; 3 inches (Box 10)
    - "SS Britannia Leaving Boston Harbor", 1969; oil, signed; , framed; 6 inches x 6 inches (Box 10)
    - Stamps, 1981-1982; 12 (Box 2)
    - "Stucco, 2 Palms, Flame Vine" for Paul Horgan, 1993; acrylic, signed; , framed; 14 ½ inches x 16 ½ inches (Box 11)
    - Study for self-portrait (Box 2)
    - Watercolor studies, 1975-1987; 9 (Box 2)
  - Prints
    - Animals (Box 2)
    - "Automatic Edgar", 1977 (Box 8)
    - "Big White Flowers", 4 (Box 8)
    - Bill/Receipt, 1976; 3; states (Box 2)
    - Bug procession, 1968; 10 prints, various states (Box 2)
    - Criminals (Box 2)
    - Film directors (Box 2)
    - Film directors (Box 8)
    - Generals, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Hartford, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Hollywood, 1973 (Box 8)
    - Indians, 1978/1979 (Box 2)
    - Insects, 1968 (Box 2)
    - "John Wayne Humping Mrs. Whistler for Jerry Falwell," undated, and "Automatic John Wayne" (Box 2)
    - "Killer Mouse in Flight", 1975 (Box 8)
    - Loan Card, 1977; 2; states (Box 8)
    - Man in flag, undated; 3; states (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1973-1982; 3 (Box 2)
    - Monkey, undated; 5; states (Box 2)
    - Self-portrait, undated; 2; states (Box 2)
    - Skeleton, 1977; 2; states (Box 2)
    - Stamp series, [1980?] (Box 2)
    - Stamp series, [1980] (Box 8)
    - "Syd & Otz First Day of Issue" with sketch, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Test prints, undated (Box 2)
    - Test prints, undated (Box 8)
    - "Waiting", 1979; 2; states (Box 2)
    - Yale, undated (Box 2)
    - Unidentified and miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Prints by others (Box 8)
  - Sketches, Notes, etc.
    - Bookplate for JWR, circa 1948 (Box 2)
    - Buildings (Box 2)
    - Calcutta project sketch (Box 2)
    - Christmas card design (Box 2)
    - "Les Miseres et Les Mal-heurs de la Guerre" (ants), 1970 (Box 8)
    - Miniature writing (Box 2)
    - Nature/Animals (Box 2)
    - Nature/Animals (Box 8)
    - People/Portraits (Box 8)
    - "Postcards from Thrishingham" (Box 2)
    - Self-portrait sketch (Box 2)
    - Sketchbooks, 2 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous sketches (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous sketches (Box 8)
  - Collages
    - T.S. Elliot in plastic frame, undated (Box 13)
    - Plexiglass and wood, undated (Box 14)
  - Book Objects
    - "An Alphabet of Indians for P.H. Indian Aficionado" for Paul Horgan, 1991 (Box 3)
    - "And These Are All the Presidents of the USA & The Verso is Their Ladies: First in War, First in Peace & First in the Hearts of Their Countrymen" for Paul Horgan, circa 1980 (Box 3)
    - "Book of Eights", 1986 (Box 3)
    - "Circa 1847-1848 Assorted American for Paul at Christmas 1980" for Paul Horgan (Box 3)
    - "Fifteen Thespians of the Golden Age" for Paul Horgan, 1990 (Box 3)
    - "Fifty Figures of the 18th Century 50 18 for P.H." for Paul Horgan, 1983 (Box 3)
    - "Great American Skulls: Charles Ives", 1985 (Box 3)
    - "Great American Skulls: Edgar Allan Poe", 1995 (Box 3)
    - "Great American Skulls: Gertrude Stein", 1988 (Box 3)
    - "Great American Skulls: William Tecumseh Sherman", 1995 (Box 3)
    - "Great River Indians" for Paul Horgan, 1990 (Box 3)
    - "Ladies" for Paul Horgan, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Memory book, sketches (Box 4)
    - Memory book, book (Box 15)
    - "The New Maclise: A Portrait Gallery of Illustrious Literary Characters" and "The Old Met: Singers in the Grand Manner at the Metropolitan Opera," for Paul Horgan, 1982 (Box 4)
    - "A Portfolio of Nine Published and Four Unpublished Drawings by Joseph Reed Comprising a Quick History of English Literature [Biographical Division]", 1976 (Box 4)
    - "16 Composers for PH," for Paul Horgan, 1982 (Box 4)
    - "Some Figure Drawings After Muybridge," for Paul Horgan, 1981 (Box 4)
    - "Something Small about Venice," for Paul Horgan, 1988 (Box 4)
    - "Thirty-four Sunsets on the Gulf of Mexico", 1985 (Box 4)
    - "This Alphabet is a Survey of the History of Western Ant," for Paul Horgan, 1983, 1982 (Box 4)
    - "Two Dozen Odd Novelists for P.H. on his Birthday," for Paul Horgan, 1980 (Box 4)
    - "The Union," for Paul Horgan, 1979 (Box 4)
    - "WW" (Whitman Sampler), 1986 (Box 4)
    - Sketches for various projects (Box 4)
    - Untitled work, undated (Box 4)
- Commissioned Work, 1972-1999; Series III
  The materials are organized into the following subseries: Alphabets; Illustrations, Medals; Certificates; Miscellaneous Designs; and Posters.
  - Alphabets
    - American Theater, circa 1981; watercolor study (Box 5)
    - "American Women", 1981-1982; prints, various states; [large] sketch for layout; final state print (Box 5)
    - "American Women", 1981-1982 (Folder 2)
    - "The Americanist Alphabet" for William Reese Company, New Haven, CT, final poster; proof poster; photographs of original art work (Folder 2)
    - "Anti-clerical Jew Alphabet" for Marshall Cohen, 1982; watercolor sketches; metal plate; notes (Box 5)
    - The Arts in America for Stinehour Press, VT, 1994; final poster; 2 layout drawings; original drawings (Box 5)
    - The Arts in America for Stinehour Press, VT, 1994 (Folder 2)
    - Bird (Box 5)
    - Bulbs, 1982; watercolor study (Box 7)
    - Colorado, 1977; prints: various states (Box 5)
    - Colorado, 1977 (Folder 2)
    - "Do You Believe in Showing the Flag?", undated; watercolor and pencil sketch (Box 5)
    - "Don't Do This to Old Glory", undated; hand-colored prints (Box 5)
    - "Don't Do This to Old Glory", undated (Folder 2)
    - Einstein, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Elizabethan Club, circa 1979; watercolor sketch; list of subjects (Box 5)
    - "Flag (Patriot)", 1981; various colors or proofs; watercolor sketches; reproduction on back of catalog (Box 5)
    - "Flag (Patriot)", 1981 (Folder 2)
    - Flowers, miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Flowers for Charles Perlitz (Box 5)
    - Freud (Box 5)
    - "Gertrude Stein", 1983; prints with painted corrections; printer's proofs; watercolor sketch (Box 5)
    - "Great British Alphabet", 1977; various states and final print (including some hand-colored, early proof) (Box 5)
    - "Great British Alphabet", 1977 (Box 7)
    - "Great British Alphabet", 1977 (Folder 2)
    - Great Smoky Mountains (Box 5)
    - "Hale Alphabet", 1997; list of proposed subjects (Box 5)
    - Harvard Alphabet, 1982-1983; source material (Box 5)
      General note
      for Harvard Magazine
    - Hebrew Alphabet, 1984; pencil sketch of letters; notes (Box 5)
      for Tim Polk Family
    - Henry James, circa 1984; proof prints (Box 5)
    - Jazz (Box 5)
    - "Learning Disabilities", circa 1991; pen and ink (Box 7)
    - "Lone State Alphabet (Texas Alphabet)", 1978; various states and artist's proof: proof prints, proof with silver ink (Box 7)
    - "Lone State Alphabet (Texas Alphabet)", 1978 (Folder 4)
    - Middletown Press, undated; watercolor sketches (Box 5)
    - Moynihan Alphabet, undated; watercolor study (Box 5)
    - Native Americans (Box 5)
    - "New York", 1978; various states of proofs (Box 7)
    - "Opera Alphabet", circa 1979; watercolor sketches (Box 5)
      for Arthur Klebanott
    - Poe, undated; incomplete, sketch for layout (Box 5)
    - Polish Alphabet, 1981-1982; watercolor study for layout (Box 5)
      for St. Mary's Church, Middletown, CT
    - St. Petersburg Alphabet, undated (Box 7)
    - St. Petersburg Alphabet, undated (Folder 5)
    - "Samuel Johnson Alphabet", 1980; final print (Box 5)
    - Samuel Johnson, 1979; list of subjects; pencil and watercolor studies (Box 5)
    - Samuel Johnson, 1979 (Folder 3)
    - "Tulip", 1983; watercolor sketch (Box 7)
      - Wesleyan University, undated; proofs, various states, with watercolor wash; pencil sketches; source material (Box 5)
      - Wesleyan University, undated (Folder 1, Folder 5)
    - Wesleyan University Campus Center, undated; watercolor and pencil sketches (Box 5)
    - Wesleyan University Campus Center, undated (Box 7)
    - Wesleyan University Campus Center, undated (Folder 5)
    - "Wesleyan University Press Alphabet", 1983; source materials; pencil sketch; printer's proofs of title; Wesleyan University Press catalog; final print; poster (Box 5)
    - "Wesleyan University Press Alphabet", 1983 (Box 7)
    - "Wittgenstein", undated; prints, some with painted corrections; painted sketch (Box 5)
    - "Wittgenstein", undated (Folder 5)
    - "Wright Brothers", 1984; notes on subjects (Box 5)
      for USIS
    - "Yale Alphabet", 1978-1979; prints; final state; pencil sketches and notes; proof prints (Box 5)
    - "Yale Alphabet", 1978-1979 (Box 7)
    - "Yale Alphabet", 1978-1979 (Folder 5)
    - Incomplete projects, undated; notes, sketches, prints (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous lists and notes (Box 5)
    - Unidentified (Box 5)
  - Illustrations
    - "Best Education Money Can Buy" [for Hartford Magazine?], 1981; acrylic (Box 8)
    - "Boswell, Laird of Auchinleck", 1977; ink sketch; source material (Box 6)
    - Clerihews of Paul Horgan, dust jacket proof (Folder 5)
    - College English, 1976, 1982; illustrations from 1976 and 1982 issues (Box 6)
    - "College English Books", 1983; cover illustration original drawing (Box 8)
    - Cradle to the Grave Book of Things to Do to Your Mom (Box 6)
    - "English in America", circa 1996; cover illustration (reproduction of cover); original drawings (Box 6)
    - "English in America", circa 1996 (Box 8)
    - Hartford Courant article by Paul Horgan, 1981 (Box 6)
    - Harvard Magazine, Seasons: Winter, Spring, Summer, 1975-1977 (Box 6)
    - Harvard Magazine, Seasons: Winter, Spring, Summer, 1975-1977 (Box 8)
    - Harvard Magazine, anthropomorphized fruit and vegetables, 1990; [gouache?]; paintings and transparencies (Box 6)
    - "He Has Long Outlived His Century…", cover illustration (Box 6)
    - Horns of Plenty: Malcolm Cowley and His Generation [journal], 1988; back cover illustration (Box 6)
    - Keys to Social Success, 1995 (Box 6)
    - Little Sisters of the Apocalypse (Box 6)
    - "Mourning Becomes Electra", 1986; program cover illustration for theater production; pamphlet; sketch; poster; paste-ups (Box 6)
    - "Mourning Becomes Electra", 1986 (Box 8)
    - "Mourning Becomes Electra", 1986 (Box 9)
    - "A Passage to India", 1980; list of proposed illustrations (Box 6)
    - "Say-brooke Colony", 1985; cover illustration for calendar; final calendar; paste-up (Box 8)
    - Three American Originals, printer's layout for dust jacket (Box 8)
    - Initial letter for "The Wesleiad," Wesleyan University English Department, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Medals
    - Correspondence, miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - American Numismatic Society, 1985; pencil sketches (Box 6)
    - American Numismatic Society, 1985; plaster model (Box 13)
    - Elizabethan Club, Yale University, 1986; pencil and watercolor sketches (Box 6)
    - Elizabethan Club, Yale University, 1986; medal (Box 13)
    - Johnsonian medal (Box 6)
    - Johnsonian medal (Box 13)
    - Johnsonian medal (Box 14)
    - Moynihan Medal (Box 6)
    - National Building Museum, Vincent Skully Prize, 1999 (Box 6)
    - Saint Anselm College competition, [198?]; pencil and ink sketches (Box 6)
    - Tinker Medal (Box 6)
  - Certificates
    - Moynihan campaign, 1981-1982; sketches for various projects; proofs of receipts (Box 6)
    - Moynihan campaign, 1981-1982 (Box 9)
    - Wesleyan University English Department, undated (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Design
    - Commission proposal for portrait of Henry VIII (Box 6)
    - Harold Hugo Memorial invitation, 1985; sketches, layout (Box 6)
    - Letterhead for Royal Oak Foundation (proposal), 1983; sketch and correspondence (Box 6)
    - Photos used for painting of E. Harold Hugo's office at Meridan-Stinehour (Box 9)
    - Program for Cover Girl, circa 1978 (Box 9)
    - Silhouette for Samuel Johnson Club of Japan, 1988 (Box 6)
    - Silhouette for Samuel Johnson Society (wine glass), 1988 (Box 14)
    - Wedding invitation, 1988 (Box 6)
  - Posters
    - "Festival of Empire," Wesleyan University of Departments of English and History, circa 1979 (Box 9)
    - "It Became Necessary to Destroy the Town in Order to Save It," New York Public Library, 1972 (Box 9)
    - "A Joyce Vaudeville: Odds & Ends from Finnegan's Wake," Center for the Humanities, Wesleyan University, 1982; sketch, final proof (Box 9)
    - "Pie Day," Wesleyan American Studies Program, 1996; sketch for poster (Box 9)
    - "Things American," Wesleyan American Studies Program, undated (Box 9)
    - "True West," Wesleyan University Department of Theatre and Dance, 1992; poster and playbill (Box 9)
    - "Two Lectures on Television," Wesleyan American Studies Program, 1990 (Box 9)